A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, New Delhi, India, RG 6, SG 7 FA396
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, field offices, New Delhi, India, RG 6, SG 7
1960-1978, undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
Rockefeller Foundation. Paris (France)
Rockefeller Foundation. Mexico
Rockefeller Foundation. New Delhi (India)
Rockefeller Foundation. Cali (Colombia)
FA396
60 Cubic Feet 149 document cases
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
RG 6.7.
Organization of the Foundation's archives:
RG 1 Projects
RG 2 General Correspondence
RG 3 Administration, Program and Policy
RG 4 China Medical Board
RG 5 International Health Board/Division
RG 6 Field Offices
RG 7 Treasurer's Office
RG 8 Comptroller
RG 9 Personnel
RG 10 Fellowships
RG 11 Information Services
RG 12 Diaries
RG 13 Oral Histories
RG 14 Counsel
RG 15 Secretary
RG 16 Minutes and Officers Actions
RG 17 Dockets
RG 18 Declinations (100F)
RG 19 Non-textual Materials
RG 20 Communications Office.
Other Finding Aids note
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices include:
FA395 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Paris.
FA397 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Cali, Colombia.
FA398 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Mexico.
FA399 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Office, Ankara, Turkey.
Arrangement note
RG 6.7 is arranged in three subgroups, corresponding to program or program area, and thereunder in series.
Subgroup I, Indian Agricultural Program, is comprised of seven series:
Series 1 - General Administrative Files Series 2 - IAP Administrative Files Series 3 - Officers' Diaries Series 4 - Crop Improvement Programs Series 5 - Agricultural Education Series 6 - Agricultural Research Institutes Series 7 - Personnel Files
In accordance with RF policy, Series VII is closed to research. Series III, Officers' Diaries, is open with the permission of the Director of the Archive Center.
Subgroup II, Medical and Natural Sciences Program, has been arranged in three series:
Series 1 - Administrative Files Series 2 - All India Institute of Medical Sciences Series 3 - Virus Research Center, Poona
Subgroup III, Humanities and Social Sciences Program, includes
Series 1 - General Correspondence Series 2 - Socio-Economic Study in Uttar Pradesh
Within series, records are typically arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material and thereunder chronologically. The original folder titles given by field office personnel at the time or records transfer to New York in 1973 have been retained. Series were established by the processing archivist in 1994.
Biographical/Historical note
From 1935 to 1973, the New Delhi Field Office of the Rockefeller Foundation (RF) administered cooperative programs throughout India in the fields of medicine and public health (1935-1973), agriculture (1956-73), and the humanities and social sciences (1964-72). The New Delhi office also served as the RF's Far Eastern regional headquarters, replacing Shanghai temporarily from 1942 to 1946 and permanently after 1949. Between 1949 and 1952, the office was located in Bangalore.
The New Delhi office was headed by the Field Director or Foundation Representative in India, who served as a scientist-cum-administrator and reported to the appropriate division director in New York. His staff included an Assistant Field Director, staff scientists and research assistants, and local administrative personnel. The field office staff was continually augmented by visiting specialists from around the world. By 1966, the fifteen-member staff in New Delhi constituted the largest RF contingent outside New York.
The RF's International Health Division (IHD) had established the first office in New Delhi for the purpose of extending its India hookworm control program, which had begun in the Madras Presidency in 1920. Subsequent medical and public health activities in India included malaria control, the development of demonstration health units, nursing education, nutrition studies, and, increasingly throughout the 1950s and 1960s, medical education and research. Significant grants went to the All India Institute of Hygiene and Public Health in Calcutta (1913-50) and the Virus Research Center at Poona (1951-71). Grants also supported the Indian Council for Medical Research and the All India Institute of Medical Sciences (1952-1973).
The last year in which grants were made in the medical field from the New Delhi office was 1970. At that time, the RF's Medical and Natural Sciences division separated into two distinct disciplines, Biomedical Sciences and Natural and Environmental Sciences.
The RF's agricultural work in India officialy began in 1956 when the Government of India and the RF signed a Memorandum of Understanding. This agreement created the Indian Agricultural Program (IAP) and spread the so-called Green Revolution to India. The IAP was the fourth in a series of ambitious "country" programs in agriculture begun by the RF in Mexico (1943) and subsequently extended to Colombia (1950) and Chile (1955). Its purpose was twofold: to increase cereal crop production through the development of high-yielding seed, and to strengthen graduate education in agriculture. Under the Memorandum of Understanding, the Government of India arranged for the necessary land and facilities and budget for local staff, while the RF provided a permanent staff of resident specialists and appropriated annual sums for equipment and other expenses incurred by the field programs. The Foundation also made grants to selected agricultural institutions and to Indian scientists to pursue research in the United States.
Research and postgraduate training were viewed as interrelated activities. In 1958, with the Foundation's support, a postgraduate school was inaugurated at the Indian Agricultural Research Institute, New Delhi (est. 1905), with the authority to award the M.Sc. and Ph.D. degrees. After 1960, new legislation made possible the creation of several state agricultural universities modeled after American land-grant universities. These universities developed relationships with the various crop improvement programs and offered valuable research opportunities for American and Indian agronomists.
The All India Coordinated Cereal Improvement Projects, the backbone of the IAP research program, represented a new approach to crop research in India. Sponsored by the Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR) and jointly operated by the ICAR and state institutions, each project studies the agronomy, entomology, pathology, genetics, and breeding of an individual crop. For the first time, research stations and substations were established throughout the subcontinent in order to coordinate research activities across the major agro-climatic zones. The programs began with maize in 1957 (although maize work had begun in India in 1945) and came to include sorghum and other millets (1957), wheat (1961), and rice (1965). Notable increases occurred in wheat production with the importation in 1965 of dwarf materials from Mexico. In conducting seed development research, the IAP benefited from the expertise of those RF agronomists who had served first in Mexico, namely Edwin J. Wellhausen, Ulysses J. Grant, Ernest W. Sprague, and the 1970 Nobel Prize winner, Norman E. Borlaug. Allied areas of research included drainage, fertility, soil and water management, and agricultural economics.
In 1973, the RF decided to bring to a close its Indian Agricultural Program. India continued to carry out crop improvement work, utilizing the administrative, teaching, and research structures jointly established over seventeen years by the IAP and the Government of India. The RF therefore phased out its involvement in all improvement programs except rice, which was continued until 1975 by Wayne H. Freeman at Hyderabad. From 1976 to 1983, the Hyderabad office under Leland R. House operated the International Crops Research Institute for the Semi-Arid Tropics (ICRISAT). This institute functioned as part of the Foundation's "Conquest of Hunger" program, which had been formally established in 1963.
In October 1964, Chadbourne Gilpatric took up residence in India as Visiting Professor in Philosophy at Delhi University, with responsibilities for representing RF interests in the Humanities and Social Sciences (HSS). Under HSS director Joseph E. Black (1964-70), Gilpatric sought to advance research and teaching in the humanities and in the social and hard sciences. He was particularly eager to strengthen curriculum at agricultural universities and to increase and preserve library holdings. From 1968 to 1972, Gilpatric coordinated a socioeconomic study of small farmers in Uttar Pradesh state. Gilpatric returned to the United States in April 1972. The Social Sciences programs had been officially phased out in 1970 and replaced with separate Arts and Humanities divisions.
Scope and Contents note
The New Delhi Field Office records (RG 6.7) of the Rockefeller Foundation Archives document the operation of the office and the programs it administered in the medical, agricultural, and social sciences. The records span the dates 1935 to 1976, but 90% of the record group dates from the period 1956 to 1973 and relates to the Indian Agricultural Program (IAP), operated by the RF's Natural Sciences and Agriculture Division. The IAP records provide a comprehensive account of the RF's role in establishing an international collaborative program of technical assistance. They also constitute an important source for the study of the history of modern agriculture and agricultural education in India.
Scope and Contents note
Important Subjects:
Agricultural education--India; Agricultural experiment stations--India; Agricultural innovation--India; Agriculture and state--India; Agriculture--Asia; Agriculture--India --Green Revolution --High Yielding Varieties Programs; Indian Council of Agricultural Research (New Delhi); Indian Agricultural Research Institute (New Delhi); International Rice Research Institute (Philippines); Plant introduction--India; Virology--Research--India; New Delhi--Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Rockefeller Foundation--India; --Rockefeller Foundation--Division of Natural Sciences and Agriculture--India; United States Agency for International Development.
Scope and Contents note
Important Names:
Allen, LeRoy R.; Anderson, Richmond K.; Baird, Guy B.; Balfour, Marshall C.; Barnard, Chester Irving; Borlaug, Norman Ernest; Bugher, John C.; Corwin, J.D.; Cummings, Ralph Waldo; Douglas, Johnson E.; Fosdick, Raymond Blaine; Freeman, Wayne H.; Gilpatric, Chadbourne; Grant, Ulysses J.; Gregg, Lucien A.; Harrar, Jacob George; House, Leland Ralph; Joshi, A. B.; Kerr, J. Austin; Mason, Max; Morison, Robert S.; Moseman, Albert H.; Pal, Benjamin Peary; Parker, Dorothy; Rachie, Kenneth O.; Rusk, Dean; Sprague, Ernest W.; Stakman, Elvin Charles; Starnes, Ordway; Strode, George K.; Swaminathan, S.; Warren, Andrew J.; Weaver, Warren; Weir, John; Wellhausen, Edwin J.; Work, Telford H.; Wortman, Sterling.
Biographical/Historical note
Rockefeller Foundation Presidents:
Max Mason, 1929-36; Raymond B. Fosdick, 1936-48; Chester I. Barnard, 1948-51; Dean Rusk, 1951-61; J. George Harrar, 1961-72; John H. Knowles, 1972-79.
Medical Program:
Foundation Representatives in New Delhi: W.P. Jacocks, 1935-42; Marshall C. Balfour, 1942-46, 1949, 1954-58; Miss J. D. Corwin, 1946-48; Richmond K. Anderson, 1948-54; LeRoy R. Allen, 1958-67; Division Directors in New York: Richard M. Pearce (Medical Sciences), 1929-30; Alan Gregg (Medical Sciences), 1931-50; George K. Strode (Medicine and Public Health), 1951; Andrew J. Warren (Medicine and Public Health), 1951-54; John C. Bugher (Medical Education and Public Health), 1955-59; Robert S. Morison (Biological and Medical Research), 1955-59; (Medical and Natural Sciences), 1964-70; John M. Weir (Medical and Natural Sciences), 1964-70.
Indian Agricultural Program:
Field Directors in New Delhi: Ralph W. Cummings, 1957-66; Guy B. Baird, 1967-71; Ordway Starnes, 1971-73; Wayne H. Freeman, 1974-75
Division Directors in New York: Warren Weaver (Natural Sciences and Agriculture), 1951-55; J. George Harrar (Agricultural Sciences), 1955-59; Albert H. Moseman (Agricultural Sciences), 1960-65; Sterling Wortman (Agricultural Sciences), 1966-70; John A. Pino (Agricultural Sciences), 1970-82.
Humanities and Social Sciences Program:
Foundation Representative in New Delhi: Chadbourne Gilpatric (Humanities and Social Sciences), 1964-72.
Division Directors in New York: Kenneth W. Thompson, acting (Humanities and Social Sciences), 1962-64; Joseph E. Black (Humanities and Social Sciences), 1964-70; Norman Lloyd (Arts and Humanities), 1970-73.
Related Archival Materials note
For information about specific grants to individuals or institutions in India, researchers should consult the grant files (1913-73) for India, located in Record Groups 1.1 and 1.2 (Projects), Series 464 (India), in the Rockefeller Foundation Archives.
RELATED MATERIALS
The following Record Groups in the Rockefeller Foundation Archives at the Rockefeller Archive Center contain material bearing upon the Foundation's work in India:
RG 1.1: Projects; RG 1.2: Projects; RG 2: General Correspondence; RG 3: Administration, Program, and Policy; RG 5: International Health Board; RG 6.13: Mexico Field Office; RG 12: Officers' Diaries; RG 13: Oral Histories, RF Field Officers.
Annual reports of the Rockefeller Foundation; Confidential Monthly Report, for the Information of the Trustees.
PHOTOGRAPHS
Four folders of photographs were removed from Record Group 6.7 during processing and added to the Photograph Collection of the Archive Center. These photographs are filed by country number, 464 India, and thereunder alphabetically by subject. They are interfiled with other photographs of India taken from Record Group 1.1 and 1.2 (Projects). Included are photographs of CIMMYT work in Mexico (n.d.), agricultural scenes in India (1958-59), compartment cages used for rearing the sorghum shoot fly (1971), and a disbound scrapbook of captioned photographs (1957) showing investigations into the virus known as Kyasanoor Forest Disease.
Conditions Governing Access note
Material more than twenty years old is open for scholarly research.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charities; Colombia; Green Revolution; Agricultural innovations; Agricultural innovations -- Mexico; Agriculture; Agriculture -- India; Medical research; India; Latin America; Life sciences; Medical education; Philanthropy -- United States; Medical research -- India; Medical sciences; Public health; Philanthropy; Social sciences -- India; Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller Foundation. Paris (France); Rockefeller Foundation. Mexico; Rockefeller Foundation. New Delhi (India); Rockefeller Foundation. Cali (Colombia)
- Indian Agricultural Program - General Administrative Files, ca. 1952-1976; I1; 21 __Boxes __6.6 cubic feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Subgroup I, Series 1, General Administrative Files (1952-1976), contains correspondence and miscellaneous materials pertaining to general field office operations. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by subject. Filed under "Government of India" are copies of agreements and understandings (1957-1976) reached between the RF and the Indian government. The bulk of the Government of India correspondence consists of letters between the field office, government ministries, and New York headquarters concerning Indian government procedures for proposing and clearing grants to agencies or institutions in India. It also covers procedures for reporting renewals, extensions, or amendments of fellowships; sending dollar checks to the United States; and preparing income tax reports. Additional correspondence concerns budgetary matters, field office bank accounts, employee housing, and staffing of the American International School, where RF staff enrolled their children.
  Other material in Series 1 is filed under the heading "Operating Records" and fills boxes 7-21. Operating records include customs clearance permits, leases for rented offices and apartments in New Delhi, personnel policy files, record-keeping procedures, and inventories of imported field equipment.
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Correspondence - Accounting/Auditing, 1961-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - American International School, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 0001a)
  - Correspondence - American International School, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 0001b)
  - Correspondence - American International School, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 0001c)
  - Correspondence - Banks - First National City Bank, New Delhi, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Banks - State Bank of Hyderabad, 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - Banks - Syndicate Bank, New Delhi, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Comptroller's Office, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Government of India - Agreements and Understandings, 1957-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Government of India - Income Tax - RF Staff, 1953-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - Government of India - Income Tax - Alexander & Company, Consultants, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - Government of India - Income Tax - Alexander & Company, Consultants, 1955-1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - Government of India - Income Tax - New York Office, 1953-1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also Box 4, Folder 26.
  - Correspondence - Government of India - RF Responses to Parliament Questions, 1954-1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence - Government of India - Policy and Procedure - General, 1958-1963, 1966-1967, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - Government of India - Policy and Procedure - Publication of Maps of India, 1965-1967, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, January-October 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, November 1970-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, June-October 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Foreign Colleagues, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Foreign Colleagues, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Foreign Colleagues, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Housing, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Income Tax, 1957-1975 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    See also Box 2, Folder 10.
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - New York Office, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Requests for Information, 1967-1973 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Visit of President John Knowles, June 1973 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous - Visitors to India, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Historical Data on RF Assistance to India, 1953-1970, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Historical Data on RF Assistance to India, 1953-1970, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Historical Data on RF Assistance to India, 1953-1970, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Historical Data on RF Assistance to India, 1953-1970, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Historical Notes on RF Assistance to India, 1952-1966 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Historical Notes on RF Assistance to India, 1952-1966 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Memoranda - Internal, 1958-1972 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Memoranda - Internal, 1958-1972 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Memoranda - Internal, 1958-1972 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Memoranda - Received from New York Office, 1959-1973 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Memoranda - Received from New York Office, 1959-1973 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Memoranda - Received from New York Office, 1959-1973 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance Permits, 1962-1974 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance Permits, 1962-1974 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Operating Records - Customs Clearance - Policy and Procedures, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Operating Records - Guest Lists, 1969-1973 (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - RF Offices - General, 1958-1974 (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - RF Offices - General, 1958-1974 (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - 6 Dharma Marg, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - Hyderabad Apartment, 1969-1971 (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - 18 Kautilya Marg, 1961-1965 (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - 27 Malcha Marg, 1968-1971 (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - 82D Malcha Marg, 1961-1971 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Operating Records - Leases and Attachments - 158 Malcha Marg, 1961-1968 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Central Government Health Scheme, 1965-1973 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Central Government Health Scheme, 1965-1973 (Box 10, Folder 68)
  - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Central Government Health Scheme, 1965-1973 (Box 10, Folder 69)
  - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Central Government Health Scheme, 1965-1973 (Box 10, Folder 70)
  - Operating Records - Personnel Policy Files - Central Government Health Scheme - Monthly Statements, 1965-1973 (Box 10, Folder 71)